Guide to the Kim Hoffmann Photograph Collection PR 77
New-York Historical Society
Kim Hoffmann Photograph Collection
1937-1980 (bulk 1949-1960)
New-York Historical Society
PR 77
5.3 Linear feet (10 boxes)
The collection primarily contains photographs of interior and industrial designs by the interior design firm Hoffmann and Heidrich. Most are interior views of New York City apartments and small retail establishments.
Provenance
Acquired by the New-York Historical Society in 1995.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
Joachim Hoffmann (February 22, 1908 - November 7, 1995) was born in Bremerhaven, Germany, and studied law and modern design for three years at the University of Berlin. He left Germany for Paris in 1933, where he practiced interior design for several years. In Paris Hoffmann began to work with the German interior designer Paul Bry; both men relocated to New York in the 1930s. Upon his arrival in New York City, Hoffman worked under the name Jo Kim as a designer and an art photographer both on his own and with Bry. Hoffmann's association with Bry dissolved in 1945, and he began a partnership with Stephen Heidrich in 1946.
Stephen Heidrich (March 22, 1891? - June 1972?) was born in Connecticut but educated in New York. While a high school student, he was awarded the Pierre St. Godin Medal for fine draftsmanship, and received a scholarship to Pratt Institute. He served in the U. S. Army during World War II. Upon his return to New York, Heidrich worked with interior designer Alfons Bach and then with celebrated decorator Dorothy Draper before forming the firm of Hoffmann and Heidrich.
In 1946 Hoffmann and Heidrich set up shop at 225 East 57th Street, and began doing interior design work for both commercial and residential clients. The majority of their designs were for New York City businesses and apartments, with some for larger homes in the surrounding suburban areas, and a few for commercial firms in Connecticut and Delaware. In addition to interior design work, Hoffmann and Heidrich designed display units for stores, and also designed furnishings and accessories for a variety of product lines and manufacturers.
Hoffmann and Heidrich favored a clean, uncluttered modern aesthetic. Their interiors were not dissimilar to those created by more high-end design firms at the same time. Their furniture, made for New York apartment living, was functional yet sleek. For example, tables were able to serve as both tables and benches. Their space-saving closet racks were popular. Both men were fine artists, interested in incorporating contemporary artwork into their residential designs. Both were also members of the American Institute of Designers.
Hoffmann and Heidrich's designs and interiors were featured in local and national newspapers and magazines such as the New York Times and Vogue, and the two often wrote articles about their designs for trade publications. By 1953 the pair were design consultants for several publications in the United States, Argentina, France, and London. In later years Hoffman gave public talks on interior design and aesthetics and taught several classes at the New School for Social Research.
Stephen Heidrich died in 1972. Hoffmann gradually stopped being an active interior designer. As late as 1980, however, he was corresponding with companies about manufacturing products to his specifications. Hoffmann died in New York City in 1995.
Scope and Content Note
The Kim Hoffmann collection spans the period from 1937 to 1980 and primarily contains photographs of interior and industrial designs by the interior design firm Hoffmann and Heidrich. The collection is divided into five series: Commissions; Installations and Trade Shows; Product Files; Publicity and Correspondence; and Personal Photographs.
While the collection is primarily concerned with the activity of the firm of Hoffmann and Heidrich, it also contains material associated with Paul Bry, and examples of both Hoffmann and Heidrich's individual work. Photos of individual designs are often stamped as such, i.e. "Design by Stephen Heidrich of Hoffmann and Heidrich." In addition, both Hoffmann and Heidrich created visual art, and photographs of Heidrich's sculptures and Hoffman's paintings are included here.
The collection was salvaged from the home of Kim Hoffmann after his death, and the photographs, negatives, transparencies, and clippings that were found were foldered by subject. The original folder titles have been maintained; in many cases they remain the only information available about the collected images. In cases where images were loose or clearly mislabeled, they were correctly refiled. However, there are still many images, mainly filed in "miscellaneous" folders, which remain unidentified. It is also unclear how much of the firm's work is documented by these records. Dates for many of the commissions were taken from the Hoffmann and Heidrich office addresses stamped on the verso of the photos.
Many of these photos were taken for publicity or for publication. Others were taken by Hoffmann or Heidrich themselves (especially their travel photography). Photos throughout the collection were taken by the following photographers: John Brefach, Ben Schnall, Clifford G. Scofield, Richard Averill Smith, William Stelling, and James Vincent. Particularly in Series III, product photographs were often samples distributed by their manufacturers.
Arrangement
The collection is diveded into five series:
Series I. Commissions
Series II. Installations and Trade Shows
Series III. Product Files
Series IV. Publicity and Correspondence
Series V. Personal Photographs
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Other photographs by Richard Averill Smith can be found in the Hewitt-Smith Photograph Collection (PR 026).
Interior designers.; Store decoration -- New York (State) -- New York.; Interior decoration firms -- New York (State) -- New York.; Commercial buildings -- Decoration -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Schnall, Ben; Smith, Richard Averill; Heidrich, Stephen; Hoffmann & Heidrich
- Series I: Commissions
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I covers the years 1942 to 1972 and is divided into three subseries: Residential Commissions, Commercial and Professional Commissions, and Hoffmann and Heidrich's Offices and Apartments. Many photos cannot be precisely dated, but span from roughly 1950 to 1960, the time of Hoffmann and Heidrich's most profitable period. Some folders contain no pictures of the actual design or renovation, but are merely a file of furniture or patterns collected for the project. Addresses for clients were often found in related clippings or from city phone books consulted for the year(s) of the work. All available material documenting each client is foldered together.
  Folders are organized alphabetically by Hoffmann's original file titles.
  - Residential Commissions
    Residential Commissions were undertaken mainly for urban apartments, and generally show living and dining rooms with a few kitchen and bedroom designs. The Melken Nursery is one of the few designs for children's room. Another is in the home of Dr. Margaret S. Mahler, a noted child psychoanalyst, who also requested a multifunctional headboard for her bedroom. The largest collection of photos in the subseries documents the renovation of Kurt and Lola Mann's home, from a heavy Tudor style to a modern and airy design. The file for Albert Drosin includes before and after pictures of the design work. A small apartment designed for Harriet Morrison highlights Hoffman and Heidrich's space-saving ideas and functionalist designs.
    Clients represented here tended to be doctors or businessmen, but also include the novelist James Ramsey Ullman and John Everett, the president of the New School. This subseries also contains a headshot of artist Ilse Getz along with photographs of her apartment redecoration.
    - Aberbach, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Arluch, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aufsessor, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Benkert, Ambrose, 220 East 73rd Street, ca. 1972 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bergman, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Blum, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Brody, Dr. and Mrs. Matthew, 41 Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn, NY, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Copen, 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Corfner, after 1957 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - Devereux, Ellis Feer, 1230 Park Ave, 1955 or later (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Donati, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Drosin, Mr. and Mrs. Albert, 118 Riverside Drive, 1957-1960 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12-13)
      General note
      See also: Box 9, Folder 162
    - Dumbke, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    - Everett, Dr. and Mrs. John R., President of New School for Social Research, 1965 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 163
    - Feuerring, Gertrude, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
    - Feuerring, Ralph, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
    - Frisch, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
    - Getz, Ilse, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
    - Gross, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
    - Haas, Edith and Loewy, Kiewe, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    - Hamburger, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
    - Heinemann, Dr. and Mrs. Martin, 75 Todd Street, Mount Carmel, CT, after 1957 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
    - Horowitz, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
    - Horyuji, after 1957 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
    - Jackson, Herb, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
    - Kaufman, after 1957 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
    - Landau, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
    - Lansdon, ca. 1952 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
    - Lasner, Westport, CT, after 1957 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
    - McTravick, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 31)
    - Mabardi, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 32)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 164
    - Mahler, Dr. Margaret, 300 Central Park West, 1956 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 33)
    - Mann, Kurt and Lolo, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34-35)
    - Melamed, Louis, Stuyvesant Town, 1949 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 36)
    - Melken Nursery, 1947 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 165
    - Morrison, Harriet, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
    - Muhlfelder, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 39)
    - Netter, Dr., 150 Central Park West, undates (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
    - Offenbach, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 41)
    - Riley, 1942 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 42-43)
    - Rockefeller, Winthrop, [before 1953] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 44)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 166
    - Rosenberg, Dr., after 1957 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 45)
    - Rosenblum, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 46)
    - Spitz, Dr., undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 47)
    - Stokvis, Mr. and Mrs. Edward, 435 East 79th St, [after 1957] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 48)
    - Udell, George, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 49)
    - Ullman, Mr. and Mrs. James Ramsey, See also: Box 9, Folder 167, 1947 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 50)
    - Unidentified prints, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 51-53)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 168
    - Unidentified color transparencies, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 54)
    - Unidentified residential plans, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 55)
  - Commercial and Professional Commissions
    Commercial and Professional Commissions primarily include small specialty stores, as well as hotel lobbies and dining rooms, restaurants, department stores, and offices. In instances where the commercial name does not reveal the store's genre, that information is noted in brackets in the container list. Offices shown include those identified as Dubinsky, Elbert, and Factor, as well as the Book of the Month Club, and Realty Associates. Several stores sell apparel, jewelry, or furs. The design of the Paulin Toy Store in Delaware seems to be a departure from Hoffmann and Heidrich's normally staid designs. The firm also designed a conference table for Nelson Rockefeller, which is included in this subseries. Other businesses represented are the East India Curry Shop and the French Government Tourist Office in New York.
    - Audrey, 40 East Palisade Ave, Englewood, N.J., 1955 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 56-58)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 169
    - Bon Ton, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 59)
    - Book-of-the-Month Club, 345 Hudson Street, 1954 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 60)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 170
    - Casual Air, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 61)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 171
    - Cheridien, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 62)
    - Dubinsky, David, [after 1957] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 63)
    - East India Curry Shop, 1947 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 64)
    - Elbert, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 65)
    - Factor, [after 1957] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 66)
    - Feldman, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 67)
    - French Government Tourist Office, 3 West 49th Street, 1958 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 68-69)
    - Green Hotel, [1946-1949] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 70)
    - Gruin Jewelry Store, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 71)
    - Hansen Glove Corp. Show Room, 1947 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 72-73)
    - J. K. Lasser Offices, 1952 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 74)
    - Marlu [hat shop], undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 75)
    - New Englander Motor Hotel, Greenwich, CT, 1960 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 76)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 172
    - New Englander Hotel, Westport, CT, ca. 1960 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 77)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 173
    - Paulin Toy Store, Wilmington, DE, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 78)
    - Alfred Rainier [fur shop], [1946-1949] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 79)
    - Realty Associates, Empire State Building, 1951 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 80)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 174
    - Rockefeller, Nelson D., undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 81)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 175
    - Rooney [dress shop], [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 82)
    - Elsa Saks Bar, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 83)
    - Transworld Feature Syndicate, [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 84)
    - Zelikow & Rebell, C.P.A., [1949-1957] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 85)
    - Unidentified prints, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 176)
    - Unidentified color transparencies, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 86)
  - Hoffmann and Heidrich Offices and Apartments
    Hoffmann and Heidrich's Offices and Apartments include all of their own offices, and several of their apartments. In at least their final address, both design showroom and apartment(s) were in the same building. The renovation of 208 East 73rd Street garnered a lot of trade press, which is included here.
    - 225 East 57th Street, Apts. 3G and 3I, [1945-1949] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 87-88)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 177
    - 208 East 73rd Street, 1957-1963 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 89-91)
    - 208 East 73rd Street, 1957-1963 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 92-93)
      See also: Box 9, Folders 178-179
- Series II: Installations and Trade Shows
  Series II dates from 1951 to ca. 1964 and primarily contain photos from several years of the National Home Furnishing Show, held in New York City. Hoffmann and Heidrich designed a variety of rooms for these shows; in 1952 they designed a recording studio for the radio show "Breakfast with the Fitzgeralds," and in 1956 a dream bedroom for actress Celeste Holm. Other photographs show product displays from unidentified trade shows.
  Folders are arranged chronologically.
  - National Home Furnishing Show
    - Combined Room, 1951 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 94)
    - Set for radio show "Breakfast with the Fitzgeralds", 1952 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 95)
      See also: Box 8, Folder 138
      See also: Box 9, Folder 180
    - Danish Kitchen, 1953 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 96)
      See also: Box 3, Folder 38
    - Celeste Holm Bedroom, 1956 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 97-98)
      See also: Box 9, Folder 181
  - Sheltered Workshop's World's Fair Nursery, ca. 1964 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 99)
  - Unidentified prints, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 100)
  - Unidentified color transparencies, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 101)
- Series III: Product and Designer Files
  Series III spans the dates from 1940 to 1980 and include products used and designed by Hoffmann & Heidrich. The firm produced industrial designs for many companies, including Congoleum-Nairn, Fabry, Hallam Kitchen, Ironmaster, and LiCo. Hoffmann also designed for Grosfeld House, and created a cabinet with copper doors painted by artist Jan Hugo.
  This series includes photographs of Eames furniture designs from an exhibit at the Museum of Modern Art in New York. Paintings and sculptures (by Hoffmann, Ilse Getz, Lotte Jacobi, and others) are also here, both as a record of artist's work, and as ideas for home decorations. The folder entitled "Swing Table and meubles ingenieus" [sic] contains photographs of furniture pieces that embody Hoffmann and Heidrich's multifunctional aesthetic. Many of these pieces appear throughout the residential commissions. Likewise, the furniture manufactured by Willow Reed was often used by Hoffmann and Heidrich in residential designs.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by Hoffmann's original file titles.
  - Antico [flooring], undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 102)
  - Automotive [flooring], [after 1957] (Offsite-box 6, Folder 103)
  - Paul Bry, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 104-105)
  - Cado/Royal System, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 106)
  - Cahn men's wardrobe, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 107)
  - Congoleum-Nairn, 1952 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 108)
  - Eames, 1946 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 109)
  - Fabry, 1954 and later (Offsite-box 6, Folder 110)
  - Flooring with models, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 111)
  - Folding Table, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 112)
  - Greymour and similar, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 113)
  - Grosfeld House, 1950s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 114)
  - Hallam Kitchen, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 115)
  - Hoffmann & Heidrich lamps, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 116)
  - Hoffmann & Heidrich various industrial design, 1950s-1960s (Offsite-box 7, Folder 117)
  - Home Bistro, 1950s-1960s (Offsite-box 7, Folder 118)
  - Hugo copper door, 1946 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 119)
    See also: Box 9, Folder 183
  - Ironmaster, 1950s (Offsite-box 7, Folder 120-121)
    See also: Box 1, Folders 12-13
  - Jacobi, Lotte, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 122)
  - Lamps, 1950s (Offsite-box 7, Folder 123)
  - LiCo, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 124)
  - Paintings, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 125)
    See also Box 2, Folder 19
  - Pelican Upholstory Company, [1949] (Offsite-box 7, Folder 126)
  - Plexiglass, 1940-1980 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 127-128)
    See also: Box 9, Folder 184
  - Emery Roth Silver, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 129)
  - Ryback figurines, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 130)
  - Sax, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 131)
    See also: Box 9, Folder 185
  - Sebastian, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 132)
  - Selling [flooring], undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 133)
  - Sheltered Workshops, [1940s] (Offsite-box 7, Folder 134)
  - Jack Soskin Associates, 1970s, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 135)
  - Swing Table and meubles ingenieus, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 136)
  - Table Settings, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 137)
  - Tancer, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 138)
  - Tewi, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 139)
  - Vulpiani Furniture Restoration, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 140)
  - Willow Reed, after 1957 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 141)
  - X-Spray Bottles, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 142)
  - Unidentified prints, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 143)
    See also: Box 9, Folder 182
  - Unidentified clippings, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 144)
- Series IV: Publicity and Correspondence
  Series IV. is divided into three subseries: Articles by Hoffmann and Heidrich, Articles about Hoffmann and Heidrich, and Other Publicity and Correspondence. Some of these articles are enlarged and laminated on 18 x 11 inch boards, possibly for display.
  Articles by Hoffman and Heidrich include several series of advice articles written by the pair for design trade magazines. The subseries also includes a few articles written solely by Kim Hoffmann.
  Articles about Hoffman and Heidrich hail from trade publications, newspapers, and foreign periodicals. Articles which refer to individual commissions have been filed with other material relating to that commission. Those here are either general articles about the firm's design ideas, or discuss commissions not represented in the client files in the preceding series.
  Other Publicity and Correspondence includes postcards sent to Hoffmann, flyers for Hoffmann's interior decorating classes at the New School, as well as several letters of reference written by psychoanalysts in support of Hoffmann's educational venture. "Your course should help your students to avoid unnecessary anxieties and compulsions which so frequently occur in the act of planning one's home," wrote Dr. Edith Jacobsen. It is likely that Hoffmann used these letters to assure students of the benefits of studying interior design with him.
  - Articles by Hoffman and Heidrich
    - Articles by Hoffman, 1952-1963 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 186)
    - Articles by Hoffman and Heidrich in Display World, Dec. 1949-Oct. 1952 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 187)
    - Articles by Hoffman and Heidrich in Playthings, Sep. 1955 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 188)
    - Articles by Hoffman and Heidrich in Sales Talk: A Digest of the Best in Selling, Apr. 1950-Mar. 1951 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 145)
    - Articles by Hoffman and Heidrich - Miscellaneous, 1951-1953 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 189)
  - Articles About Hoffmann and Heidrich
    - In Interiors & Industrial Design, Feb. 1946 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 190)
    - In Vogue, Oct. 1947 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 191)
    - Miscellaneous, 1947-1970 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 192-193)
  - Other Publicity and Correspondence
    - New School of Social Research class bulletins, 1965-1971 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 146)
    - Letters from psychoanalysts, re: Hoffmann's classes at NSSR, 1973 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 147)
    - Postcards sent to Hoffmann, 1961, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 148)
    - Unused letterhead, 1940s and later (Offsite-box 8, Folder 149)
- Series V: Personal Photographs
  Series V includes Hoffmann and Heidrich's travel photography, miscellaneous personal photographs, and photographs of interiors in Berlin and Paris, as well as New York. The pair traveled to Italy, Dubrovnik, and other locales along the Mediterranean. The series also contains contact sheets from a party given by Hoffman and Heidrich for the artist Maria Boerner around 1958, as well as a negative of a photographic portrait of Hoffmann.
  The series is divided into Travel Photos and Miscellaneous.
  - Travel Photos
    - Berlin (Steinhurz), 1940s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 150)
    - Dubrovnik Contacts [Sheets], ca. 1965-1975 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 151)
    - Italy 71, 1971 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 152)
    - New York Scenes, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 153-154)
    - Paris, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 155)
      See also: Box 10, Folder 194
    - Unidentified travel photos, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 156)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Boerner, Maria Party, ca. 1957 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 157)
    - Interiors - Berlin, Paris, New York, ca. 1940s -1950s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 158)
    - Portrait of Hoffmann, before Mar. 1953 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 159)
    - Porges, 1961-1962 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 160)
    - Miscellaneous prints, 1937-ca. 1970s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 161)
- Oversize Material
  - From Series I: Residential Commissions